Guide to the Karl John Richard Arndt Collection of Bernhard Muller and the Harmony Society
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Karl John Richard Arndt collection of Bernhard Muller and the Harmony Society
1721-1984
WA MSS S-2690
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
10.08
(12 boxes)
The papers document Karl Arndt's research on the Harmony Society in the United States, 1805-1905, (including its leaders Johann George Rapp and Frederick Reichert Rapp) and the settlements founded by Bernhard Muller, also known as Count Leon (including the New Philadalphia Congregation, 1832-1833 and the settlement of Germantown, Louisiana, 1833-1871). Material includes Arndt's collection of primary sources, his research files, including photocopies of other documentation, and the draft of his three-volume work Des Messias Wiederkehr. Also included in the collection are books from Johann Georg Goentgen's library
Arndt, Karl John Richard
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Chapel Hill Rare Books on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 1993.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arndt, Karl John Richard, 1903-1991
Karl Arndt, born in St. Paul, Minnesota in 1903, was a scholar of German-American history specializing in utopian societies. He was a professor at Louisiana State University from 1935 until 1947, and at Clark University, where he was head of the German Department from 1950 to 1969. He served in the United States Military Government in Germany, in the Office of Church-State Relations, from 1945 to 1950. Arndt wrote several volumes of history on the Harmony Society, including George Rapp's Harmony Society, 1785-1847 (Rutherford, New Jersey: Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 1972).
Muller, Bernhard (Count Leon), 1788-1834
Bernhard Muller, also known as Count Leon, Proli, and Archduke Maximilian von Este, was born near Frankfurt, Germany in 1788 and as a young man gave sermons predicting the onset of the millennium, which created conflict with Church and State officials. He immigrated to the United States in 1831, first living in the Harmony Society in Butler County, Pennsylvania, and later founding the separatist New Philadelphia Congregation (in present-day Monaca, Pennsylvania) and, in 1833, the settlement of Germantown, in Grand Ecore, Lousiana. Muller died of yellow fever in Germantown in 1834.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents Karl Arndt's research on the Harmony Society in the United States, 1805-1905, (including its leaders Johann George Rapp and Frederick Reichert Rapp) and the settlements founded by Bernhard Muller, also known as Count Leon (including the New Philadalphia Congregation, 1832-1833 and the settlement of Germantown, Louisiana, 1833-1871). Material includes Arndt's collection of primary sources, his research files, including photocopies of other documentation, and the draft of his three-volume work Des Messias Wiederkehr.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Primary material, 1721-1937. II. Secondary Material, 1775-1984. III. Writings of Karl John Richard Arndt, undated.
German Americans -- Louisiana -- Religious life; German Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Religious life; Utopias -- United States; Butler County (Pa.) -- Religious life and customs; Louisiana -- Religious life and customs; Natchitoches Parish (La.) -- Religious life and customs; Pennsylvania -- Religious life and customs; Arndt, Karl John Richard; Goentgen, Johan Georg; Muller, Bernhard, -1832; Rapp, Frederick, 1775-1834; Rapp, George, 1757-1847; Harmony Society; New Philadelphia Society
- Primary Material, 1721-1937; Series I; 7.42 linear feet (8 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged according to Karl Arndt's numbering of sources (chronologically in two groups).
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of Arndt's collection of primary sources used for his research on Count Leon and his involvement in nineteenth-century German-American religious sects. Material includes documentation of the organization and leadership of the Harmony society, the New Philadelphia Congregation, and Germantown, Louisiana, printed material by and about Harmonists and Leonites, correspondence to and from sect members, photographs of residents of Germantown, Louisiana, maps used when the Leonites journeyed from Pennsylvania to Louisiana, and books from Johann Georg Goentgen's library.
  Document numbers in parentheses reflect Arndt's identification of the material. Material is also identified by number in a detailed list of collection contents filed in Box 1.
  - Correspondence, manuscripts and printed material (documents 1-60), 1825-1836; 54 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, manuscripts and printed material (documents 61-125), 1836-1860; 53 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, manuscripts and printed material (documents 126-177), 1861-1937; 54 (Box 3)
  - Vision books (documents 178-182), 1721-1847, undated; 5 (Box 3)
  - Manuscripts, maps, and photographs (documents 183-199), 1832-1880; 19 (Box 4)
  - Manuscripts, maps, photographs, and printed material (documents 200-208), 1832-1904; 14 (Box 5)
  - Books from Goentgen's library in Germantown, 1765-1803; 10 (Box 6)
  - Books from Goentgen's library in Germantown, 1810-1826, undated; 7 (Box 7)
  - Manuscript material from Goentgen's library in Germantown, 1828-1858; 4 (Box 8)
- Secondary Material, 1775-1984; Series II; 2 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Arranged as received by the Beinecke Library.
  Series II consists of Karl Arndt's research files on Count Leon and the Harmony Society. The files include printed material, photocopies of newspaper articles and other documents. Arndt numbered some of the material as a separate series of documents (1B-44B). Other material is unnumbered.
  - Research files, including photocopies of manuscripts and other documents (documents 1B-44B), undated; 43 folders (Box 9)
  - Research files, including photocopies of manuscripts and other documents (unnumbered documents), 1775-1984, undated; 37 (Box 10)
- Writings of Karl John Richard Arndt, undated; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series III consists of Karl Arndt's draft of Des Messias Wiederkehr, a history of Count Leon and the Harmony society. The work is divided into three volumes. The drafts of Volumes 1 and 2 appear complete, while the third appears incomplete.
  - Des Messias Wiederkehr, draft, typescript, corrected, undated; 5 (Box 11)
- Oversize Material, 0.25; (1 box)
  - Adelsbrief von Johann Peter Heuser, 1797, copied 1825 (document 1) (Series I) (Box 12)